11th Infantry Brigade, War Diary, August 1914

Appendix 4

TO: HANTS - E. LANC - RIF BRIG - S.L.I.
Sender's Number: B.M. 4 | Day of Month: Thirtieth | In reply to Number:

The march will be resumed at once to the original destination via Trosly Bruille AAA. Battalions will join the line of march as they find it most convenient AAA As long as each battalion marches smartly and as a complete unit. The G.O.C. Division will take the salute at a point on the road near MORENVAL Fm. AAA

From | ELEVENTH INF BRIG
Place | TRACY-le-MONT
Time | 2.13 pm

TO: Gen'l Haldane Comdg Rear Guard
Sender's Number: B.M. 3 | Day of Month: 30th | In reply to Number:

Ref my B.M.2, I find that the road the division has taken leaves TRACY-le-VAL well on the left, and goes direct from BEAILLY via OLLENCOURT to TRACY-le-MONT. AAA

From | ELEVENTH INF BRIG
Place | ½ mile S.E. of BAILLY
Time | 8.30 am

operation Order No 1

Maj. Gen. T D'O Snow CB Comdg 4th Div

30.8.14

1.  The news of the situation tonight is most satisfactory. The enemy's advance has been checked, both against our right & our left. The situation however requires a short strategical retirement on the part of the 4th Div, but the G.O.C. 4th Div knows that the troops in the Div will willingly respond to yet another exceptional call on their morale.

2.  The Div will march in one column. March table is attached. This march table has been issued to some units as a warning order.

3.  The Div will move tommorrow to the line of the River AISNE.

4.  There will be a long halt probably of 2 or 3 hours at 8 am during which troops will be feed & horses watered.

5.  The withdrawal of the outposts will be arranged so that PONT L'EVEQUE is clear by 6 am.

6.  The bridge mentioned in above para will be blown up by R.E. by order of rearguard commander 4th Div.

7.  Refilling point & supply rendezvous have been specially arranged for.

8.  The no. 15 & 2 Fd Amb'ces having rejoined the Div, the A.D.M.S. will detail one to march after the 11th Inf Brig & the other with the rearguard which is will meet at the cross roads ¼ mile east at 6 am.

9.  Div. H.Q. in CARLEPONT MAIRIE will be closed at 5 am & repoen at the same time at the head of the 11th Inf Brig.

[Signed]

Issued at 2.15 am

4th Division

March Table attached to Op Order No 1 of 30.8.14

Unit | Starting Place | Time
Supply Section | cross roads ¼ mile east of T in CARLEPONT | 3.15 am
Train (less Supply Section) | | 3.31
9th Fd Co. RE. | | 3.40
37 F.A.B. | | 3.44
14 F.A.B. | | 4.10
12th Inf Brig | | 4.24
32 F.A.B. | | 4.44
Div Hd Qrs & No 1 Sctn Sig Co. | | 5.8
11th Inf Brig | | 5.10

Rear Guard

Commander - Brig Gen Haldane

10th Inf Brig
120th FAB
Cyclist Co.
7th Fd Co. R.E. will join at N in SEMPIGNY.

To be South of the line PONTOISE BRIDGE - SEMPIGNY by 6 am.

Route

Road junction ¼ mile east of T in CARLEPONT - I of CHAMP DU MERLIER - TRACYLEMONT to TROSLY BREUIL.

TO: HANTS - E.LAN - RIF BRIG - SOMERSETS - 14 Bde R.F.A.
Sender's Number: BM 2 | Day of Month: Thirtieth | In reply to Number:

The 11th Inf Brig will form up on the CARLEPONT - LESCLOYES road in the lfoowing order: - HANTS - R.B. - S.L.I. - E.LAN - AAA The head of the column opposite E.LAN bivouac at 4.40 am AAA The detachements now under Col BIDDULPH will form up on the side of road opposite their bivouacs in time to join their units as they pass. AAA

ROUTE. Road jcn ¼ mile E of "T" in CARLEPONT - "I" of CHAMP-du-MERLIER - TRACYLEMONT to TROSLY BREUIL - AAA

The 14th Bde R.F.A will march at such hour that the head of their column reaches the road jcn ¼ mile E of "T" in CARLEPONT and will follow the 37th Bde R.F.A.

From | ELEVENTH INF BRIG
Place | S house but one in village of LESCLOYES
Time | 3.45 am

TO: Eleventh Brigade
Sender's Number: AA 150 | Day of Month: Seventh | In reply to Number:

GOC wishes you to forward at your earliest convenience a short account of the action of troops under your command at the battle of LIGNY - HAUCOURT - SEVIGNY on 26th August together with a list of officers, warrant officers, NCO's and men who you want to bring to notice for their good service AAA The list should not exceed 15 names and should be arranged in the order of merit which you consider their actions justify AAA In each case a short account of the reason for your recommendation should accompany each individuals name.

From | Fourth Division
Place | VILLENEUVE LE COMPTE
Time | 9.35 am

11th Infantry Brigade, War Diary, August 1914

Appendix 5

TO: Som LI - E. Lancs - Hants - 9 Coy RE - Div Am Col.
Sender's Number: B.M. 6 | Day of Month: 31st | In reply to Number:

All transport (2nd line) and supply wagons must be at the top of the hill about FAYFE FARM tonight. They will proceed by the road leading through the second I in SAINTINES.

From | Eleventh Bde
Place | Road junction just W of C in Courselle
Time | 11.40 pm

TO: 4th Div
Sender's Number: B.M. 3 | Day of Month: Thirty first | In reply to Number:

On visiting the outpost line from St. SAUVEUR - MALINAUX - HOURPARI I found the 4th Middlesex Regt had taken up outposts on this line intermingled with the E. LAN. Regt which already held it. I instructed the Middlesex Regt to withdraw their groups and form a support to the E. LAN pending further instructions. As placed the two lines of outposts were a serious menace to each other.

From | Brig. Maj. 11th Inf Brig
Place | St SAUVEUR
Time | 9.29 pm

TO: 4th Div
Sender's Number: B.M. 1 | Day of Month: Thirtyfirst | In reply to Number:

The Brig will move west this morning via ST JEAN AU BOIS - ST SAUVEUR. The 10th & 12th BRIGS will be moving via PUITS DU ROI - PONT DE LA CROIX - VERBERIE.

STARTING POINT - Railway bridge pt 87. This will be pointed out to units by Bde Maj & Staff Capt - the heads of units will arrive at starting point as follows:-

ADVANCE GUARD
1 Bn R.B.  Comdr Col BIDDULPH

9th Fd Co R.E. | 7 am
11th Inf Bde (less 1 bn)
1 Coy of Hants | 7.5 am
32nd Bde R.F.A. | 8.50 am
Train 11th I B (less supply sects) | 10.15 am
Rear Gd (1 Coy Hants Rgt) | 10.45 am

Order of march 11th Inf Brig:-

SOM. L. I. 7.5 am. E LAN 7.10 am - HANTS 7.15 am

2.  All sick will be evacuated by supply section of train to refilling point.

3.  Refilling point will be on fork roads at first V at VILLENEUYE.

4.  Reports to head of Left column.

5.  Mounted representatives of units will meet the Brigade Major and Staff Captain at the MARIE at 6.30 am when they will be shown the route to the starting point.

From | 11th Inf Bde
Place | CHATEAU PRIORIE
Time | 5.20 a.m.

Operation Order No 1

Appendix to the Op order No 1 of 31 August

31.8.14

1.(a)  The French met with great success in the neighbourhood of GUISE, where the German Guard & 10th Corp were driven back to the OISE. The French forces were also engaged yesterday in the direction of PERONNE.

b)  Our Cavalry are holding the OISE south of COMPIEGNE. The Secornd Army Corps advances on our left.

2.  The Fourth Div. will move west in two columns today, as shown in the march table attached. Each column will find a small rear guard.

3.  All sick will be evacuated by supply secns of train to refilling point.

4.  Railhead & supply rendezvous for supply column - LE PLESSIS BELLVILLE (15 miles S.W. of CREPY).

5.  Refilling point will be on fork of roads at first V of VILLENEUVE.

6.  12th Fd Ambce will detail medical officer, 3 Fd ambces & necessay personell to accompany right column & march in rear. 10th Fd Ambce will detail medical officer & 1 Fd ambce and necessary personell to accompany left column & march in rear.

[page torn] Reports to head of left column.

[Signed]

Issued at 2.15 am

Appendix to Op Order No 1 of 31.8.14

March Table

Unit | Starting Point | Starting Time | Route

Right Column

Comdr Brig. Gen. Wilson 12th I.B.

Advanced Guard

1 Bn. 10th I.B.

| | | Cross roads 1 mile west of MOUNT BERNY - PUITS DU ROI - PONT DE LA CROIX - VERBERIE

Main Body

Comdr Brig. Gen. Wilson 12th I.B.

10th I.B. (less 1 Bn)

| Cross roads 1 mile west of MOUNT BERNY | 7 am |
fproo

19th I.B.

| - " - | 7.25 am |

12th I.B.

| - " - | 8.10 am |

3 Fd ambces of 12th Fd Ambce

| - " - | 8.35 am |

Left Column

Advanced Guard

1 Bn. 11th I.B.

Div Cyclist Co.

| | |

Main Body

Div. H.Q. | A | 6.50 am |

RUE MELONN - ST JEAN AUX BOIS - ST SAUVEUR

"A" starting point is the cross roads ½ mile S.W. of MOUNT BERNY

"B" starting point is the cross roads by the F in FONTENOY

Troops in 12th Brig area using 'B' starting point must not pass through the cross roads 1 mile west of MOUNT BERNY

9th Fd Co. R.E. | D | 6.55 am
11th I.B. (less 1 Bn) | B | 7 am
29th F.A.B. | A | 7.15 am
14th F.A.B. | B | 7.45 am
1 Bn 11th I.B. (less 1 Co) | B | 8.15 am
37th F.A.B. | A | 8.10 am
32nd F.A.B. | B | 8.45
7th Fd Co. R.E. | A | 9.5 am
10th Fd. Ambce. | B | 9.20
12th Fd. Ambce. (less 3 ambces) | A | 9.15
Fd. Vet. Secn.
Train (less supply secns.) | B | 9.25
12th I.B. | A | 9.40
10th I.B. | B | 9.55
11th I.B. | B | 10.10
Div. Am. Col. | B | 10.35

Rear Guard

1 Co. 11th I.B.

War Diary – 11 Inf Bde

August 1914

Hour, Date, Place

|

Summary of Events and Information

|

Remarks

18th Aug. '14

|

Brigade moved from COLCHESTER to HARROW ON THE HILL, where the 4th Div. concentrated by 19th Aug.

|

21st

|

Brigade entrain at HARROW & proceed to SOUTHAMPTON. Hd Qrs, 1/Som. L.I. 1/E. Lancs, ½ Batt'n 1/Hants embark on BRAEMAR CASTLE & sail to HAVRE. Disembarkation completed by 9 a.m. 23rd.

|

23rd

|

Hd Qrs entrain at 10 p.m. for Rest Camp at HAVRE. Rest of Brigade entrained during night and early hours of Aug 24th.

|

24th

|

Brigade commenced to detrain at LE CATEAU about 4 pm. Finished about 4 am 25.9.14. Brigade H.Q.rs at BRIASTRE. Somerset L.I. and E. LANCS billeted at BRIASTRE.

|

25th 4 am

|

Somerset L.I. and E LANCS advanced to positions respectively S.W. and S.E. of SOLESMES.

|

25th 11 am

|

At ll am the Hants & Rifle Brigade arrived at BELLE VUE. The Hants were sent to strengthen the E. Lancs SE of SOLESMES and the Rifle Brigade were sent to the S.W. of SOLESMES, ½ Bn to prolong the line of the S.L.I. to the E., ½ Bn in reserve. Thus covering the retirement of the 7th Brigade which formed the rearguard of the 3rd Division moving S.W through ROMERIES on SOLESMES, and the 19th Brigade retiring through SOLESMES from the N.N.W.

|

Appendix 1

25th 11 pm

|

At 11 pm the Brigade retired to VIESLY, greatly impeded by transport which was hopelessly blocked in the village of VIESLY, forming a rearguard with the 10th Brigade to the N. After passing VIESLY the 10th Brigade took over rearguard to the 4th Division. The Brigade retired via BETHENCOURT - BEAUVOIS - FONTAINE-AU-PIRE where it arrived at 2.45 am on August 26th & billeted.

|

August 26th 1914.
FONTAINE-AU-PIRE.
LIGNY.

|

Battle of LIGNY

After the retirement from LIGNY, the Brigade was split into two portions, the Brigade H.Qrs and a portion of each battalion of the Brigade retired via CAULLERY - ELINCOURT to SERAIN arriving about 8 pm and billeting there. The rest of the Brigade retired through SELVIGNY - MALINCOURT to VILLERS-OUTRÉAUX where they billeted.

|

Appendix 2

August 27th 1914

SERAIN 2.30 am

NAUROY 8.30 am

NAUROY 8.30 pm

|

Hq Qrs Wing of Brigade retired at 2.30 am cross country under local guidance skirting the N of BEAUREVOIR in order to escape the congested roads - just N of ESTREES to NAUROY, where the G.O.C. decided to make a 3 hours halt, till 11.30 am, but at 10.45 am it was reported that the Uhlans had been seen in the next village and shell fire was almost immediately observed on the village. The troops retired somewhat disorganised. H Qrs, the E. Lancs and fragments of other battalions to the S.W. across the canal under cover of a long strip of wood to PONTRU - VERMAND - ATTILLY - ETREILLERS - FLUGIÈRES - AUBIGNY to HAM where they arrived about 8.30 pm and took up outposts about ST. SULPICE after a march of about 35 miles.

|

Aug 27th (cont'd)   NAUROY

|

The other portion of this Wing chiefly the Rifle Brigade, E Lancs and Hants retired W through VILLERET turning S and eventually joining the 4th Division during their night march to VOYENNE: at TERTRY.

|

VILLERS-OUTRÉAUX 3.30 am

|

The other Wing of the Brigade left VILLERS-OUTRÉAUX at 3.30 am and marched to LE CATELET where Hd Qrs 4th Division were found. The march was immediately resumed to ROISEL where the Division rested till the evening. Colonel Biddulph with a portion of the Rifle Brigade was at LE CATELET and he assumed command of this portion of the Brigade. From ROISEL a night march was made by the Division to VOYENNE via VRAIGNES - MONCHY, arriving about 5 am 28th Aug.

|

Aug 28th VOYENNE 8am

|

The B.G.C. rode over from HAM and assumed command about 8 am, leaving the other wing under the command of Col LE Marchant. The retirement was resumed about 10 am via LIBREMONT where a halt of 2 hours was made, the march being resumed at 8 pm to FRENCICHES where the troops bivouaced along the road till dawn. The wing of Brigade under Lt. Col Le Marchant marched to PONT L'ÉVÈQUE via main road through GUISCARD, and bivouaced there.

|

Aug 29th FRENICHES 3.45 am

|

Retirement resumed via MUIRANCOURT, where the 12th Brig was passed, to SERMAIZE where this Wing of the Brigade halted till 6 pm, at this hour the march was resumed to the PONT L'ÉVÉQUE via the western suburbs of NOYON wherein orders were received to continue the march to the village of LES CLOYÉS which was reached about 11 pm.

|

Aug 29th (cont'd) PONT L'ÉVÈQUE

|

The Wing under Col LE Marchant moved from PONT L'ÉVÈQUE at 4 pm through a large wood along an indifferent track which caused some delay to the transport, to LES CLOYES where the whole Division was bivouaced, and here the two wings of the Brigade at length became united.

|

Appendix 3

Aug 30th LES CLOYES

|

Soon after daybreak on Aug 30th this Brigade moved as part of the division via CARLEPONT - BAILLY - TRACY-LE-MONT - TROSLY-BREUIL to PIERREFONDS, this was a particularly trying march. PIERREFONDS was not reached till after dark, bivouacs were difficult of access, and billetting was impossible owing to a reported outbreak of smallpox: consequently the troops spent a wretched night in the streets.

|

Appendix 4

Aug 31st PIERREFONDS 6 am

|

On this day the march turned westward through the forest of COMPIÈGNE via ST. JEAN-AU-BOIS to ST. SAUVEUR. The Brigade was to have billeted in SAINTIMES and arrangements had been made - but development in the situation caused a change of plans and the Rifle Brigade were ordered to COURCELLES and SOMERSET L.I. to the high ground S of ST SAUVEUR. The HANTS and the E. Lancs found the outpost line to the E of the village. The 1st line transport was ordered to VERBERIE.

|

Appendix 5

REPORT ON ACTION OF 1/EAST LANCASHIRE REGIMENT OF THE 27th/28th AUGUST, 1914

TNA: WO 95/1486/1, pp 29-30

copy

Fourth Div

In accordance with verbal instructions from G.O.C. 4th Div, I have the honour to bring to notice the action of the 1st Bn East Lancashire Rgt on the 27th - 28th Aug 1914.

This battalion with some detachments from other units of the 11th Infantry Brigade, in their endeavour to rejoin the Headquarters of the 4th Division, from which they had got separated after the battle of the 26th, marched (35) thirty five miles in 26 hours without food other than the little that was procurable from the villages en route, and yet marched into HAM and through HAM whistling and singing about 7 pm on 27th.

After getting some food (there was not much to be got) from supply wagons south of HAM, this battalion immediately marched back 2¼ miles (37¼ in all) and took up an outpost line covering HAM from the North. This outpost line they held all night until relieved by the 3rd Division the next morning.

HAM was at that time the headquarters of the 2nd Army Corps.

This instance of endurance, cheeriness and fine military spirits is the more worthy of record when it is remembered that these men had been marching and fighting without intermission from the time they got out of the train at LE CATEAU at 4 pm on the 24th, that they had held the FONTAINE-AU-PIRE position for 10 hours under heavy fire, that they had been heavily shelled both at LIGNY and in their retirement from that place on 26th, and that further on the 27th at NAUROY they had again been shelled by the pursuing horse artillery.

The principal credit for this meritorious performance is due among the Officers to

Lt Col le MARCHANT

whose example of cheeriness & self-possession, and whose handing of the men was beyond praise.

Lieut & Adjt BELCHIER

who was indefategable in keeping the men together & in making arrangements for such food and rest as was possible to find them.

Among the N.C.Os & men the following are those most worthy of mention.

C.Sgt Maj Burgess, Sergt Pattinson

These N.C.Os were invaluable throughout in controlling and encouraging tired men. Both showed gallantry and coolness when the column was shelled by pursuing Artillery and by their example did much to keep the men together

A Hunter-Weston
Brig Gen'l
Comdg 11th Inf Brig

Bucy
2.10.14

TNA: WO 95/1486/1, p 31

Record of march of the portion of the 11th Inf Brig under B.G.C. on 26th/27th Aug 1914.

Left LIGNY | 5pm
26.8.14 | ... 7¼ miles | ..35 miles
(in 26 hours)
Arrd SERAIN | 8pm
26.8.14
Left SERAIN | 2am
27.8.14 | ... 27¾ miles
Arrd HAM | 7pm
27.8.14

Note. The E. Lancs outpost companies marched an additional 2¼ miles, a total of 37¼ miles in about 28 hours.

D'Orsy Capt
1.10.14

TNA: WO 95/1486/1, p 32

Headquarters 11th Infantry Brigade

Herewith roll of Officers and N.C.Os present with the Battalion at Ham.

Lt Col Le Marchant D.S.O
Major Lambert
Capt Coventry
Capt Clayhills D.S.O
Capt Goldie
Lieut Hughes
Lieut Hopkinson
Lieut MacMullen
Lieut Delmege
2Lieut Tosswill
2Lieut Wade
Lieut Richards
Lieut Belchier
CSM Burgess
Sgt Neow
CS Wilkinson
Sgt Pattinson
Sgt Woodman
Sgt Cuttle
Sgt Hill
Sgt Noden
Sgt Barnes
Sgt Corbett
Sgt L'Anson
Sgt Thompson
Cpl Norton
Cpl Coultrip
Cpl Upjohn
Cpl Halliwell
Cpl Thistle
Cpl Jaggers
Cpl Knoght

I have no record of Officers & N.C.Os. of other regiments who were with this party.

K Belchier Lt for Lt Col
Comdg 1/E. Lanchashire Regt.

Bucy
30.9.14

11th Infantry Brigade, War Diary, September 1914

Appendix 6

TO: Brig Gen Hunter Weston.
Sender's Number: SH 41 | Day of Month: First | In reply to Number:

It is not proposed that the outposts found by the troops in various areas should link up. You will therefore be responsible for the protection of the whole perimeter of your area. The area at FRESNOY and the combined areas of BARON & VERSIGNY are each providing their own protection. AAA Divn HdQrs is at BARON.

From | 4. Div.
Place | BARON
Time | 6 pm

TO: Eleventh Brigade.
Sender's Number: G 37 | Day of Month: First | In reply to Number:

Reference my G26 Innis. Fus. now at RARAY are quite happy. Report that they were in difficulties incorrect aaa You can now therefore retire by a shorter way aaa You are to act as rearguard to the force till you reach the line MT CARNON - RARAY when rearguard duties will be taken over by 12 & 19 Brigades and you will march and take up position at FRESNOY LE LUST. 10th Brig evacuating wounded & captured German guns from NERY. Get in communication with them aaa They have been ordered to retire through 19 & 12 Brigs on the line DUCY - BOASNES. Innis Fus have been ordered back to BEAULIEU LE NEUF where they will rejoin the Brigade. 12 and 19 Brigs as soon as they have covered retirement of 10 & 11 Brigs will retire to BEAULIEU LE NEUF and MONTEPILLOY respectively.

From | 4. Div.
Place | RARAY
Time | 12.45pm

TO: Eleventh Brigade.
Sender's Number: G 26 | Day of Month: First | In reply to Number:

Orders received from Corps HdQrs that we are to retire slowly first on line Mt CORNON - CHAMICY then on FRESNOY LE LUST - MONTEPILLOY aaa General situation 9.30 am - 12th Brig Mt CORNON, 10th Brig between SUCITERIE DE NERY and LA BOISSIERE Fe with one battn at NERY. 19th Brig FAY Fe helping BRIGGS who is said to be engaged with Germans at VANCELLES. aaa Inniskilling detatched from 12th Brig are about ST VAAST. They have been shelled in VERBERIE and had better come under you. This is your authority to take them over for the present. Gen wishes you to retire approximately on the line DE LONGMONT point 126 RARAY - CHAMICY withdrawing the Inniskillings as you pass ST VAAST and letting 19th Brig know what you are doing if possible. Latter should retire by FAY Fe LA BARDE Fe - RULLY keeping touch with you and 10th Brig. If you can get in touch with them pass this message on at once. Div H.Q. will move at 10 am to North end RULLY.

From | Fourth Division
Place | Point 126
Time | 9.45pm

TO: HANTS - E.LAN - SOMERSETS - RIF BRIG - 14 Bde R.F.A. - 29th Bde F.F.A. - 7th Fd Co R.E. - 11th Fd Amb.
Sender's Number: BM 2 | Day of Month: First | In reply to Number:

The 4th Div moves today in the direction of BARON via BULLY

(2) March will begin on 2 roads, but the column will join on to one road at point indicated later and thence continue to BARON.

(3) Each unit must ensure being in touch with the unit in front of it, so that there may be no delay in moving off.

(4) The rearguard of Eastern column in which the 11th INF BRIG are included will be joined by the 32nd Bde R.F.A. on reaching LA BARDE Fe (1 mile N.E. of RARAY) and take over rear guard duties for whole div.

(5) 11th Fd AMB at VILLENEUVE will join the column at RARAY and follow the 10th Fd AMB. All men unable to march will be carried by Fd AMB and not on wagons of units.

(6) Refilling point for 4th DIV St MARD.

(7) Reports to present hdqrs till march beings then to head of rear guard.

(8) The 1st line transport (less fighting portion, E.LAN & HANTS) will follow the 7th Fd Coy R.E. under Lt MacMullen E. LAN.

Times of arrival at starting Pt will be notified as soon as received.

From | ELEVENTH INF BRIG
Place | COURCELLES
Time |

TO: ROURTH DIV.
Sender's Number: B.M. 4 | Day of Month: First | In reply to Number:

The bearer of this message (Capt O'Mahoney) reports that a force of German Cavalry, strength a division which advanced from the direction of PIERREFONDS towards ROCQUEMONT being repulsed by gun and rifle fire, retired hurriedly in a S.E. or E. direction. AAA I an holding the St SAUVEUR ridge with infantry (2 bns) along the bottom of the hill. As the right of this front line is rather in the air, I am withdrawing it to take up a shore position on the St SAUVEUR ridge, N of BETHISY facing N and E. I have pushed forward one bn in the direction of the firing this morning to occupy the high ground S of BETHISY. AAA My infantry N of St SAUVEUR have been firing at a few of the enemy's patrols. I shall continue to hold the St SAUVEUR position AAA I should add that from what Capt O'Mahoney states there would appear to be no German Infantry in the immediate vicinity. AAA I suggest that this officer's motor would be very valuable for inter-communication between you and me until I leave the St SAUVEUR position.

From | ELEVENTH INF BRIG
Place | COURCELLES
Time | 7.32 am

TO: Eleventh Brigade.
Sender's Number: One | Day of Month: 1/9/14 | In reply to Number:

Our position is as follows. One Coy direct on St LUCE FARM and nearby there one Coy in position facing NERY on the edge of the ravine half mile South of the V of VAUCELLE. Two Coys in reserve about the first E of VAUCELLE AAA About a squadron of the cavalry has reached ST LUCE.

There appears to be a general advance of our troops from the direction of SAINTINES towards NERY and the West of NERY.

From | Rif Brig
Place | just E of VAUCELLE
Time | 8.33 am

Operation Order No 1

Chateau of VERBERIE

1-9-14

Reference BEAUVAIS & SOISSIONS sheet.

1.(a)  The 4th Divisopn & 19th Inf Brig will move today in direction of BARON via BULLY.

2.   The march will begin on two roads but the column will join on to one road near RARAY at a point which will be indicated, and continue the march to BARON in one column.

March table attached. Troops to be ready to move at 7am.

3.   The time of starting of the first unit in each column will be notified as soon as orders are received from Army Corps H.Q.

Each unit must ensure being in touch with the unit in front of it on the line of march so that there may be no delay in moving off when the order to march is received.

4.   Div Amm Col will start for BARON at 4 am and the Train at 5 am. 19th Inf Brig Train and Amm Col with march with the 4th Div Train.

5.   The Rear Guard of eastern column on reaching LA BARDE Fe will be joined by the 32 FAB and will then take over the duties of rear guard to whole division.

Cyclist Co. North Irish Horse & 10th Fd Ambce will send representations to 11th Inf Brig by 5 am for orders.

The rearguard of the western column will remain out until rear of its main body has reached neighbourhood RARAY when it will hand over its duties as rearguard to rearguard of eastern column and rejoin its brigade at the first opportunity.

11th Fd Ambce at VILLENEUVE will join the column at RARAY and will march in rear of 10th Fd Ambce.

6.   All men unable to march will be carried by Fd Ambce and not on wagons of units.

7.   Refilling point for 4th Div and 19th Inf Brig will be at ST MARD.

8.   Reports to CHATEAU VERBERIE till march commences, after that to head of western column, and after RARAY at head of Division.

Lt Col, Gen Staff 4th Division

Issued at 2 am

War Diary – 11 Inf Bde

September 1914

Hour, Date, Place

|

Summary of Events and Information

|

Remarks

Sept 1st  ST. SAUVEURS. 6am |

On this day the march was resumed southward, the 11th Brigade being detailed as rearguard to the Division. Before moving off about 4.30 am the enemy attacked the E. Lancs. posts at the E end of ST SAUVEUR village, with machine gun & shrapnel fire. The Somerset L.I. were ordered to take up a position about FAY Fm and the Rifle Brigade on the high ground S of VAUCELLE village to cover the retirement of the other two battalions.

|
10am |

The E. Lancs and Hants retired with a few casualties via the NERY valley. An attack on the Rifle Brigade & Soomerset L.I. was repulsed with considerable loss to the enemy. The retirement was then continued in small columns across the open plateau, the right of the Brigade being directed on MT. CORNON, the left on CHAMICY. The Brigade billeted at ROZIÈRES which had been evacuated by a force of Uhlans only an hour or two before. The water here was very bad.

| Appendix 6
Sept 2nd  ROZIÈRES. 1.30am |

The Brigade moved from ROZIÈRES in the direction of NANTEUIL to avoid the possibility of shell fire in the village.

|
3am |

About 3am orders were received directing the march on DAMMARTIN. The Brigade turned about & marched via BARON to EVE where it billeted for the night. The 19th Brigade coming from FRESNOY found the rear guard, but on arrival at EVE they passed through, leaving the 11th Brigade as rearguard.

| Appendix 7
Sept 3rd  EVE. midnight
12 noon |

March resumed about midnight 2nd-3rd Sept via DAMMARTIN - CLAYE - LAGNY - CH. FONTINELLE. Arrived there about 12 noon. Very hot day, bivouac moved from N side of LAGNY - VILLENEUVE-LE-CONTE road to the woods about CH. FONTINELLE.

| Appendix 8
Sept 4th  CH. FONTINELLE. 3pm |

Short march N.W. to COUPVRAY. Outposts from MONTRY to railway station NW of COUPVRAY in touch with 5th Divn on the right. It was reported that the enemy had constructed a pontoon bridge across the river during the night, but in the morning it was found to be driftwood only.

| Appendix 9
Sept 5th  COUPVRAY. 3.30am |

The Brigade moved via JOSSIGNY - FERRIÈRES - OZOIR-LA-FERRIÈRE to CH. MARSAUDIÉRE and acted as rearguard to the division, finding outposts along the railway from OZOIR to GRETZ. First reinforcements joined the Brigade this day.

| Appendix 10
Sept 6th  CH. MARSAUDIÉRE. 8.30am |

The Brigade marched North to VILLENEUVE-LE-CONTE via FERRIÈRES and JOSSIGNY. The Brigade was in reserve.

|
Sept 7th  VILLENEUVE-LE-CONTE. 6am |

The Brigade moved about 6am via VOULANGIS - CRECY-LA-CHAPELLE to MAISONCELLES. The 12th Brigade was in the advanced guard, the INNISKILLEN Fusiliers losing some men through a surprise machine gun & shell fire NW of village. The Battalions of the Brigade were bicouaced all round the village each finding outposts.

|
Sept 8th  MAISONCELLES. |

The Brigade having withdrawn their outposts moved off from the crossroads W of LA BARDE (the starting point) as part of the Left Colm of the Division about 8 am, and marched via LA-HAUTE-MAISON - halting here for an hour while the 19th Brigade moved forward as an advance guard, - PIERRE LEVEE to SIGNY-SIGNETS. At a point about ¾ mile N of this village the 19th Brigade came under heavy & accurate shell fire from the high ground about MORINTRU-LE-HAUT. Our Artillery came into action as quickly as possible, but they were somewhat delayed by the 1st line transport of the 19th Brigade in front of them. The enemy's fire was soon silenced, and few casualties occurred on our side.

The 11th Inf Brig moved eastwards through LES CORBIERS to CH. VENTEUIL and then billeted, outposts being found to the N and W as well as protection for the Artillery just S of CH. VENTEUIL. The 12th Brigade prolonged the line to the E. Two battalions of the 19th Brigade remained in position on the high ground S of SAMMERON facing N and connecting with out left. Both bridges at LA FERTÉ were demolished by the enemy.

|
Sept 9th  CH. VENTEUIL. 6am.

Sept 9th (Contd)  LA FERTÉ |

After a careful officers' reconnaissance, the Brigade was moved by a steep track leading N.E. over the PETIT MORIN river at ST MARTIN. The Rifle Brigade & Somerset LI were sent to occupy the high ground S of TARTEREL. The E. Lancs occupied LA FERTÉ village S of the MARNE River watching the two broken bridges.

The enemy was occupying the houses along the N bank of the river with snipers and machine guns making any movement in the open on our side impossible. The Hants were kept in reserve at CH. VENTEUIL. Our artillery heavily bombarded the enemy in and about LA FERTE and our machine guns and snipers inflicted considerable loss on the enemy, their casualties were estimated by inhabitants at about 700, whereas our loss cannot have exceeded 30.

In the evening and during the night the 12th Brigade and the Rifle Brigade crossed the MARNE river by the railway bridge N.E. of CHAMPIGNY. Two Coys E. Lancs and one Coy Hants, afterwards followed by the remainder of both battalions, ferried across the river in rowing boats close to the eastern bridge at LA FERTÉ. During the night a pontoon and barrel bridge was thrown across the river at this point.

| Appendix 12
Sept 10th  LA FERTÉ. 9.30am. |

At 9.30am H.Q. and the Somerset L.I. passed over the bridge leaving one company as rearguard. This Coy waited till the RE had demolished the bridge and rejoined the Brigade next day. The Brigade assembled in column of route on the main LA FERTÉ - CHATEAU-THIERRY road about a mile N of LA FERTÉ. Some delay was caused while the Rifle Brigade rejoined from the NE after having crossed the river with the 12th Brigade as mentioned above.

About 2.30pm the Brigade moved on via PORTE-FERÉE - COCKEREL to billets at CHATON and RADEMONT where the night was spent. The 11th Brigade was the rear Brigade of the Division. H.Qrs 11th Inf Brig were at RADEMONT.

| Appendix 12
Sept 11th  RADEMONT. 4am. |

The Brigade advanced at 4am, the two battalions at RADEMONT namely E. Lancs and Rifle Brigade marching via OCQUERRE - COULOMBS road on the W bank of the OURCQ river, while the Somerset L.I. and Hants marched direct from CHATON to VENDREST joining the remainder of the Brigade on the main road NW of VENDREST; the march was then continued via COULOMBS - HERVILLIERS - St. QUENTIN, to which place the Brigade was conducted along a track across country by an officer of the Divisional staff. The track leading N.W. from CERFROID Fme and saving a march of about 2 miles. The transport had to go round by the main road through MONTIGNY L'ALLIER and FULAMES. A halt of about 2 hours was made at ST. QUENTIN till 2.30 pm, during which time the 12th and 19th Brigades, which had gone round by the main road, passed through us.

| Appendix 13
2.30pm. |

The march was resumed in pouring rain to PASSY-EN-VALOIS which was reached about 5 pm, and here the Brigade billeted for the night. The Rifle Brigade had been left to billet at a farm about 2 miles SW of PASSY. The 11th Brigade was again in rear of the 4th Division.

|
Sept 12th  PASSY-EN-VALOIS. 8am. |

The Brigade resumed the advance at 8am, in showery weather and along bad roads via MARIZY-ST-GENEVIÈVE - MARIZY-ST-MARD - CHOUY - ,where it passed through the 19th Inf Brigade, - VILLERS-LE-PETIT - LOUATRE - VILLERS-HÉLON - MONTRAMBOEUF Fm - where a halt of half an hour was made; instructions were here received from the 4th Division to draw up the Brigaded in mass behind the ridge about Pt 132 ½ mil S.W. of RAPERIE to be in reserve with the 12th Brigade in the same formation immediately E. of it, but after a short haly the Brigaded was ordered on via VILLEMONTOIRE - ROZIERES - ECATRY - SEPTMONTS which was reached at dusk in pouring rain about 6.30 pm.

|
6.30pm. |

Here troops were billteed in a very confined space, soaked through and having had no issue of food for the day, till 10pm when a further advance was made to BUCY-LE-LONG and the heights N of it.

| Appendix 15
Sept 13th-20th  BUCY-LE-LONG. |

Vide Appendix 15.

| Appendix 15
Appendix 16 a.b.c.d.e.f.g.h
Sept 21st  BUCY-LE-LONG. |

No change in the situation. E.Lancs were withdrawn from the trenches and the Rifle Brigade moved from reserve to take their place. The E. Lancs machine guns were left in position at the top of the ravine either side of the BUCY-LE-LONG - VREGNY road.

| Appendix 17
Sept 22nd 1914.  BUCY-LE-LONG. |

The situation still remains the same. The Rifle Brigade lost one man killed through a post being rushed. The Somerset L.I. killed a German artillery officer in the early morning by sniping. The makes the eleventh man they have killed this way since we have been here.

Listening patrols report, as on the previous two or three nights that during the evening between 7 and 9 pm a great movement of transport was taking place along the MAUBERGE road. - About 360 reinforcements arrived last night, - 3rd reinforcements.

| Appendix 18
Sept 23rd  BUCY-LE-LONG. |

Soon after midnight it was reported from 4th Division that the French 6th Army was to make an attack on our left at dawn, the 11th Inf Brigade to assist this attack as far as possible but not to make any offensive movement themselves.

The Somerset L.I. sent 2 platoons forward to a ridge about 200 yds in front of their trenches to assist with fire, but no attack took place, it was afterwards stated owing to the mist.

A slight advance was stated to have been made by the French about 11am, but there was little firing, and apparantly little ground was gained.

The enemy was reported at 7.10 pm to have been digging a trench 800 yds in front of the Dublin Fusiliers left and to the right front of the Rifle Brigade. Orders were issued for a careful reconnaissance to be made during the night.

There was no real change in the situation.

566 Reinforcements arrived for the Brigade in the Evening - 4th reinforcements. A party of about 120 stragglers arrived in the early morning.

| Appendix 19
Sept 24th 1914.  BUCY-LE-LONG. |

No change in the situation, a very quiet day. The reconnaissance made during the night proved it was not a new trench which the enemy had yesterday been reported to be digging, but an improvement and extension of an old one. Notification was received about 6pm that the French 6th Army would renew the attack at dawn tomorrow, the 11th Brigade to be ready to support such attack.

| Appendix 20
Note. |

From the 10th September till September 22nd there was almost incessant rain, with rare intervals during which it was impossible for the men to dry their clothes properly. Despite this bad weather, the health of the troops has been remarkably good, only 10 men being admitted to hospital sick during the last week at BUCY-LE-LONG. A party of 51 stragglers arrived in the evening.

|
Sept 25th 1914.  BUCY-LE-LONG. |

Another quiet day without change. The French attack which was to have taken place at dawn was again postponed, official notification of this was not received till 8am. The only firing which took place today was at aeroplanes; this fire was entirely without effect.

| Appendix 21
Sept 26th 1914.  BUCY-LE-LONG. |

No change in the situation.

Trenches, more especially the machine gun pits were still further improved.

The G.O.C. 4th Division inspected the whole line of trenches from 5.30 am to 8 am.

The The Rifle Brigade shot one man of a german patrol at dawn.

The weather reamined fine.

Notifcation oa a further french attack on LA PERRIÈRE Fm to be carried out tomorrow was received in the evening. A staff officer was sent to the H.Qrs of the french 90th Brig to find out exact time of attack, with a view to our cooperating as far as possible. This officer remained at ST. PAUL all night, as the hour of the attack was not then fixed.

| Appendix 22
Sept 27th 1914.  BUCY-LE-LONG. |

Situation unchanged.

The Zonares on our immediate left advanced their trenches 50 to 150 yards but these trenches were untenable during the day owing to the enemys heavy shell fire, one or two men only were therefore kept in them.

There was a good deal of sniping on both sides but no casualties. Trenches were still further improved. Summary of information up to Sept 26th and War Diary of a German Adjutant is attached to Appendix 23.

| Appendix 23
Sept 28th 1914.  BUCY-LE-LONG. |

Situation still unchanged.

The G.O.C. 4th Division visited the Rifle Brigade and Hampshire Regt trenches at 6.30 am. The B.G.C. ordered new trenches to be dug connecting Capt Jones-MORTIMER's advanced post with the Somerset L.I. H.Qr. cave also a trench firing up the shallow valley running N.E. from the above situationed post and in front of this post. Arrangements were made for the E. Lancs (in reserve) to carry out this work at dusk and during the night.

Lt Col Lawrence arrived to take over command of the E. Lancs. There was very little artillery during this day. The french advanced trenches on our left were shelled rather heavily. Sketch showing german trenches and summary of information is attached to App 24.

| Appendix 24
Sept 29th 1914.  BUCY-LE-LONG. |

No change in the situation.

Further reinforcements arrived in the evening for the Rifle Brigade of 1 officer an 93 other ranks. 5th reinforcements.

About 8 pm a Somersets patrol reported enemy deploying from 3 columns, and it was supposed an attack was intended but nothing happened.

Capt YATEMAN's communicating trench to his forward observation post was completed and Capt JONES-MORTIMER completed the fire trenches in front of his forward post. The new forward trench between the Somerset L.I. H.Q. cave and Capt JONES MORTIMER's post was commenced during the night 28th-29th Sept, 50 yards still remain to be dug (vide App 25)

A copy of Summary of Information up to 29th Sept 1914 and of Extracts from Diaries etc are attached to App 25. An account of the retirement of the E. Lancs Regt from LIGNY to HAM on Aug 26-27th is attached to App 25.

| Appendix 25
Sept 30th 1914.  BUCY-LE-LONG.
2.45pm |

No change in situation.

At 2.45pm notification was received of an intended trench attack on LA PERRIERE Fe at 3pm with the usual orders for the 11th Brigade to assist as far as possible. This attack never developed into a very serious affair, and little or no progress was made. Our artillery assisted by firing on the batteries at LA PERRIERE Fe and Point 132. Vide reports attached to App 26. Record of daily casualty returns upto and including Sept 30th is attached to App 26.

Maj DE LA CHAPPELE, Rifle Brigade was appointed Brigade Transport Officer.

Note. An amended account of the action of 11th Inf Brig on night of 12th-13th Sept is attached to App 26.

| Appendix 26

War Diary – 11 Inf Bde

October 1914

Hour, Date, Place

|

Summary of Events and Information

|

Remarks

October 1st  BUCY-LE-LONG |

Confidential orders received in afternoon for the 4th Division to extend its right and take over the trenches occupoed by the 5th Division to enable the latter to withdraw. The 11th Infantry Brigade took over trenches originally occupied by the Dublin Fusiliers; for disposition of Battalions see App 27.

| App 27
11pm |

Somersets advanced post killed 4 germans (Pomeranians). Situation otherwise unchanged.

Note - Number of sick evacuated in the Brigade during the week 25th Sept - 1st Oct inclusive = 28.

|
October 2nd  BUCY-LE-LONG |

Situation unchanged.

The Rifle Brigade shot 8 germans during the day, and it is now reported that 6 were shot last night making a total of 14.

Summary of Information to 30th Sept and "Tall Tales from the Trenches" is attached to App 28.

| App 28
October 3rd  BUCY-LE-LONG |

Situation unchanged.

Gen Sir H. Rawlinson inspected trenches of Hants & R.B. in the early morning.

The R.B. dug new forward trenches N.W. of LA MONTAGNE Fm to join up with the new trenches of the Seaforth Highlanders, during the night Oct 3rd-4th.

| App 29
October 4th  BUCY-LE-LONG |

Situation unchanged.

R.B. new trenches further improved. Quiet day. No casualties.

|
October 5th  BUCY-LE-LONG
10am
8pm |

Situation unchanged.

Order to move received at 10am, but cancelled at 4.30pm owing to the French being unable to take over.

The E. Lancs ? bulk of transport at 8pm.

| App 30
October 6th  BUCY-LE-LONG |

Situation unchanged.

Moved to BUZANCY and VILLEMONTOIRE after dark. The remainder of transport left about 6.30pm, the two reserve companies per Battalion at 7.30pm, and the remaining two companies from the trenches at 1am. Somersets and B.H.Qrs billeted at the CHATEAU BUZANCY. The Hants and Rifle Brigade at VILLEMONTOIRE.

| App 31
October 7th  BUZANCY |

Stayed all day in billets. The Brigade left shortly after midnight and marched via HARTENNES to PLESSIER-HULEU and BILLY-SUR-OURQ in which places it billeted.

| App 32
October 8th  PLESSIER-HULEU |

Marched at 4.30 pm via ST. REMY - CORCY - FLEURY where there was a 2 hour halt - VILLERS-COTTERETS and were billeted at 2am in LAGNY and VEZ.

| App 33
October 9th  LAGNY and VEZ |

Brigade moved about 2.30pm & marched via LE PRESSOU - ELMCOURT - ORROUY arrived 7pm and billeted at BETHISY.

| App 34
October 10th  BETHISY |

Brigade moved about 3pm; the Somersets and E. Lancs to entrain at COMPIÈGNE. B.H.Qrs, HANTS, Rifle Bde marched via MERVILLERS to ESTRÉES-ST-DENIS wher they entrained at 11pm.

| App 35
October 11th  In Train |

Train left at 2.30am via ABBEVILLE and CALAIS to ST. OMER arriving about 5.30pm and the Brigade marched to billets at BLENDECQUES arriving at 7pm.

|
October 12th  BLENDECQUES |

Motor busses were expected at 1pm, they began to arrive in small numbers at 8pm and it was not until 1.30am next morning that the whole Brigade had started to move, and the lat bus load finally reached HONDEGHEM at 6am on Oct 13th, the distance was only 12 miles.

The transport was ordered to move at 11.30am and arrived at 4.30pm many hours in advance of the infantry, with nothing to cover it from attack: a position of great insecurity!

| App 36
October 13th  HONDEGHEM |

The 11th Inf Brigade marched at 10am as reserve to the 4th Div, the 10th Brigade finding the advanced guard. Opposition was met about METEREN but the 11th Brigade was not drawn into the fight and billeted at FLÈTRE. The HANTS had been taken away about 5pm as a reserve to the 12th Brigade. The SOMERSETS foud outposts east of FLÈTRE.

Steady rain in the afternoon.

| App 37
October 14th  FLÊTRE |

Brigade moved at 9am in a north-easterly direction towards MONT NOIR, but after 2 miles this march was diverted to METEREN, thence to BAILLEUL again as an advanced guard. The E. Lancs and Rifle Brigade found outposts along the line of V in NEUVE ÉGLISE - Pt 40. The Hants and Somersets billeted in the lunatic asylum. B.H.Qrs at Pt 77.

| App 38
Ref OSTEND sheet SET 'A' sheet I, 1:100000
October 15th  BAILLEUL |

The 11th Inf Brigade again furnished advanced guard, & moved about 5 pm along main BAILLEUL - ARMENTIÈRES road. No opposition was met with as far as cross roads ½ mile North of RABOT. From this place a night attack on NIEPPE and ERQUINGHEM bridge was made. E. LANCS to attack NIEPPE from the North via ROMERIN, the HANTS due East along the main road, and the Somersets with the RB in reserve and 2 sections RE to attack the ERQUINGHEM bridge.

NIEPPE was entered unopposed and a reconnaissance proved the ERQUINGHEM bridge intact and not held. At midnight an order was received from Army H.Qrs not to proceed further: Units were therefore billeted for the night with adequate protection. The Hants had 12 casualties, being fired on by machine guns about the bridge over the river between NIEPPE and ARMENTIÈRES.

Sepecial appendix of documents & sketches held back is here inserted.

| App 39
Special App 1
October 16th  Cross Roads ½m N of R of RABOT |

No change in situation. HANTS in billets in NIEPPE with outpost line across main road ½ a mile East of NIEPPE. Somersets continuing the line to the South through HALTE to LE MENEGATE afterwards pushing forward to ERQUINGHEM bridge which they held.

| App 40
Oct16th cont'd   4pm |

At 4pm an attack was made on some machine guns which were holding the PONT DE NIEPPE. After shelling the barricade for a short time the enemy retired, and the Hants occupied the bridge. The 12th Brigade moved to billets about PLOEGSTEERT, the 10th Brig moving up from BAILLEUL to billets about LA CRÈCHE. Quiet night.

Special order of the day of 16th Oct and Summary of Information 16th Oct is att'd to App 40. Also Summary of Information Oct 18th.

|
Oct 17th  Cross Roads ½m N of R of RABOT |

10th Brigade moved forward at 7am via ERQUINGHEM bridge through ARMENTIÈRES to a line about 1 mile east of this town. 12th Brigade held line from HOUPLINES to LE GHEER. The 11th Brigade in reserve in yesterdays billets. Bat'ns dug in.

| App 41
Oct 18th  Cross Roads ½m N of R of RABOT
6.30am |

Headquartes left ESTAMINET AU SEAU.

| App 42
(Order of the day 17th Oct and Composition of XIX Saxon Corps is attached to App 42)
7am |

11th Brigade was assembled at NIEPPE.

|
10.34am |

11th Brigade marched to billets about ARMENTIÈRES, E. LANCS and RB at the lunatic asylum, S.L.I. and HANTS near Railway station.

|
4.30pm |

Brigade orderd to attack PREVOTÉ in order to fill gap between 6th Division and the right of the 10th Brigade, but B.G.C. having ascetained that the gap was already filled and darkness coming on, decided not to act on these orders.

|
|

During the night E. LANCS dug trenches astride Railway about 800x east of Asylum facing east. RB remained in bivouac at asylum. L'EPINETTE was captured by 10th Brigade during the night 18th-19th.

|
Oct 19th   Rly station HOTEL. ARMENTIÈRES. |

R.B. moved to deep trenches on east side of railway immediately east of asylum. HANTS to billets on road 400x south of station, SOMERSETS just south of Railway on ERQUINHEM road, these two battalions being in Corps reserve. E.LANCS remained in trenches. A quiet day.

R.B. moved to HOUPLINES in evening, they and E. LANCS to serve Divisional reserve. HANTS moved back to station.

3rd Army HdQrs established in ARMENTIÈRES.

| App 43
(Summary of Information Oct 18th is attached to App 43)
Oct 20th   Station HOTEL. ARMENTIÈRES.
1am |

In operation orders. Whole Brigade ordered to form Divisional Reserve.

|
7.30am |

ARMENTIÈRES shelled for a short time by howitzers.

|
8.15am |

HANTS moved from station to ERQUINGHEM road just North of Railway for safety.

|
9.50am |

E. Lancs sent to reinforce 17th Brigade owing to PREMESQUES having been taken by enemy. This battalion was held in reserve at WEX MACQUART being ordered to dig trenches east of this place facing east as a second line of defence.

| vide E.L 20
App 44
(Composition of VII Corps and Summary of Information & sketch Oct 19th is attached to App 44)
12.30pm |

HANTS ordered to move forward to establish 3 posts east of lunatic asylum 3 Coys in front and 1 in reserve, the whole as a second line of defence behind the WARWICKS and DUBLIN FUSILIERS.

|
1.15pm |

SOMERSETS ordered to proceed to PLOEGSTEERT to check enemy who appeared to be attempting to turn the left flank of the 12th Brigade, they marched via PONT DE NIEPPE and LE BIZET. They came under orders of B.G.C. 12th Brigade.

During the afternoon the R.B. dug trenches North east of HOUPLINES under orders of B.G.C. 10th Brigade.

|
2pm |

Som L.I. and E. Lancs ordered to form Corps reserve.

| Ref GGG5
5.10pm |

11th Inf Brigade revert under command of G.O.C. 4th Div.

| G 315
7.25pm |

Operation orders received q.v with regard to disposition of 11th Brig.

|
10.40pm |

10th Brig report disposition of R.B. at HOUPLINES.

| H 177
Oct 21st   Point 63
3am |

11th Brig HQrs, E. LANCS less a company and a platoon with 1st and 2nd echelon transport left ARMENTIÈRES, crossing river by pontoon bridge via LE BIZET to PLOEGSTEERT.

| App 45
5.30am |

Heavy firing heard east of road near LE GHEER which afterwards proved to have resulted in the capture of LE GHEER by the enemy.

|
Oct 21st (cont'd)
6am |

E. LANCS less a company and a platoon reached PLOEGSTEERT and were placed under orders of O.C. 12th Inf Brig who sent them forward to reinforce the INNISKILLEN FUSILIERS, who had been driven back.

| App 45
6.20am |

SOMERSETS arrived at Point 63.

|
6.30am |

Brig H.Qrs established at Point 63.

|
8.30am |

SOMERSETS launched to counter attack the enemy who had captured LE GHEER, in cooperation with 2 companies E. LANCS who were ordered to advance against LE GHEER along the south edge of BOIS DE PLOEGSTEERT. The SOMERSETS were ordered to move north of the BOIS DE PLOEGSTEERT through ST YVES and along the east edge of the above wood with the machine guns firing dow the outside of the wood.

The E. LANCS well led through the wood by CAPT NORTH, staff captain 12th Brig, were able to enfilade a large number of germans along a shallow ditch to the south of the wood, and killed and wounded about 40.

The SOMERSETS worked south through the east edge of the wood and advancing the attack captured the village of LE GHEER from the north. As soon as the SOMERSETS had captured the village and cut off the retreat of the germans, some INNISKILLENS advanced from the west, and the E. LANCS charged out of the wood to the South. The enemy was completely bewildered and ran in all directions. 130 prisoners were taken and the enemy's casualties are estimated at 1000 at least. We lost 85 Killed and Wounded. - It was a most successful affair very well carried out.

Detailed accounts of this action from Battalions are attached to App 45.

| In connection with this action messages of congratulation were received from (1) CinC. att'd App46; (2) G.O.C. 4th Div GGG14 App45; (3) G.O.C. 2nd Cav. Div embodied in message from B.G.C. 11th I.Bde to S.L.I. BM4 App45; (4) O.C. 12th Inf Brig
The following officers were brought to notice: MAJOR J GREEN; LIEUT & ACT. ADJ. F.E. BELCHIER; LIEUT F.D. HUGHES (All EAST LANCS REGT)
11.27am |

LE GHEER reported recaptured.

| SL 8
3pm |

2 Coys HANTS rejoined Brigade from ARMENTIÈRES.

The line of our trenches was heavily shelled in the afternoon.

|
4pm |

Orders were issued for a general defensive line to extend from the E of WARNAVE R. to the R of DOUVE R. to be divided into 3 sections between E. LANCS, SOMERSETS, HANTS from right to left respectively.

R.B. still at HOUPLINES under 10th Brigade.

HANTS less 2 Coys at lunatic asylum ARMENTIÈRES.

|
6pm |

HANTS less 2 Coys ordered to LE TOUQUET to be under orders of 12th Brigade.

2 Coys R.B. ordered back to Asylum to be followed by the remainder when they can be spared.

|
|

Later, one company HANTS and machine gun relieved KINGS OWN at PLOEGSTEERT. One company HANTS sent to LANC. FUSILIERS. Two companies R.B. ordered to LE BIZET to be in Div'n Reserve. 11th Brigade ordered to take over trenches of 12th Brigade as soon as possible.

| Operation orders
Oct 22nd   POINT 63.
5am |

Enemy made an attack along line ST. YVES - LE GHEER - LE TOUQUET but were very easily repulsed.

2 Coys RB moved to LE BIZET during the night 21st-22nd.

| Ref OSTEND MAP, scale 1:100000
6am |

Crossroads ¼ mile S of E of WARNAVE reported by 12th Brigade reoccupied during the night without opposition.

| B.M.5
8.24am |

The two Coys HANTS on the left of the line placed under command of Mahor Prowse. Two coys SOMERSETS to be in Brig reserve near the junction of the ST YVES road with the main road.

| B.M.8   App 46 (Message of congratulation from C-in-C attached)
9.30am |

Brig HdQrs moved to crossroads at PLOEGSTEERT.

| B.M.7
1.55pm |

R.B. detailed to take over south of the defensive line to crossroads ¼ mile SE of V in WARNAVE R not inclusive.

| B.M.15
4.30pm |

Dispositions of Brigade to be assumed during night are detailed in BM16 attached to App 46.

| B.M.16
9.15pm |

Report sent to 4th Div on position of Enemy's machine guns.

| B.M.19
11.59pm |

HANTS report 2 coys in trenches, one in reserve, one still at LE TOUQUET.

| B.M.19
Oct 23rd   PLOEGSTEERT Xroads.
7am |

11th Brigade reported established on north & south line between rivers LYS and DOUVE vide App 47.

| BM 5.   App 47
7.30am |

12th Brigade report all its units have been relieved.

| BM 1
9.30am |

RB report having taken over trenches by 9 pm previous night and started a new trench on their right, they ask for R.E. section tonight.

| RB 2
8.26am |

SOMERSETS in trenches with cavalry on their left.

|
8.44am |

E. LANCS ask for a gun to be brought up to destroy a house from which the enemy commanded his trenches.

| EL 2
8.59am |

SOMERSETS report having located 2 enemy machine guns.

| SL 2
12.55pm |

HANTS send rough sketch of their trenches (attached to App 47).

|
5.48pm |

R.B. report signalling communication was established with SEAFORTHS on their right at 1.30 pm.

| RB 8
7.30pm |

Russian victory near WARSAW reported by 4th Div.

RB sketch map of position of trenches attached to App 47.

| G 17
Oct 24th   CAFÉ ROYAL PLOEGSTEERT.
12.50am |

Information received from 4th Div of 1st Corps success on our left 1000 reported dead and 500 prisoners.

| G 20
1am |

An attack by enemy on our trenches commenced extending along the sections occupied by the E. LANCS, SOMERSETS and HANTS. It continued for about an hour, and was easily beaten off. Our artillery afforded valuable support.

|
6.8am |

SOMERSETS report that the enemy did not leave their trenches, being prevented from doing so by the excellent shooting of the Artillery.

| SLI
6.15am |

R.B. report all quiet last night.

|
8.19am |

4th Divn report likelihood of a general attack by Enemy during the day, but it never came off.

| App 48
10.33am |

32nd Bat RFA report that their howitzers have obtained two direct hits on a house which contained enemy's machine guns.

| 105.
11.55am |

Headquarters established at CAFÉ ROYAL. PLOEGSTEERT.

| BM 13
12.2am |

Aircraft report received from 4th Divn.

| G 6
12.noon. |

Notification received from 4th Div of the recommendation of Brig Gen Hunter-Weston for immediate promotion.

| G 8
4.45pm |

4th Div reports 1st Corps counted 1500 dead germans and between 600 and 700 prisoners belonging to 23rd Reserve Corps yesterday.

The following documents are attached to Special Appendix 2:

(1) Sketch maps showing disposition of company trenches 24.10.14; (2) Russian official communication; (3) Message from C in C; (4) Map showing enemy's trenches as ascertained from aerial observation; (5) Movements of 4th Division; (6) Summary of Information

| Special Appendix 2
Oct 25th   CAFÉ ROYAL PLOEGSTEERT.
6am |

All units report a quiet night, & situtation unchanged.

SOMERSETS report CONNAUGHT RANGERS in position on their left.

| S.LI.   App 49
8.39am |

RB suggest that an officer from the SEAFORTHS on their right should come to their observation post and note the position of some terraced houses, which were loopholed, with a view to getting the R.A. to shell these houses if required.

| RB 2
6pm |

RB report as to advisability of using STATION as a point d'appui to cover any retirement.

| RB 3
11.20pm |

Report sent to 4th Div that a flare light had been lit at 11pm and sharp machine gun & rifle fire commenced lasting ¼ of an hour on our centre & left. Also that our lines to 4th Div, E. LANCS & SOMERSETS were disconnected.

| BM 6
Oct 26th   CAFÉ ROYAL PLOEGSTEERT.
5.40am |

A small attack with machine guns was made on the E. LANCS during the night.

| EL 2
5.45am |

RB report more sniping than usual during the night, and that owing to the enemy having burnt a stack, it was impossible to work much at entanglements.

|
5.50am |

SOMERSETS report situation unchanged. Enemy sent up star shell during the night but made no attack, apparently they feared an attack by us.

| S.LI.
7.45am |

Orders given for E. LANCS to releive the two companies in trenches tonight.

| BM 2
10am |

Civilian work on reaer line of trenches resumed, supervised by 3 E. LANCS Subaltern officers and Capt SYMONS R.E. This is the third day civilians have been employed at this work, and they have done it remarkably well.

| BM 3
10.50am |

Notes re method of taking over trenches in the defensive line issued to units.

| BM 5
10.50am |

RB report germans attacking SEAFORTHS in FRELINGHEM, enfilade fire is brought to bear from R.B. trenches, abd the ARTILLERY cooperate.

The SEAFORTHS have been obliged to fall back to their prepared rear trenches owing to enemy's shell fire, all other trenches held firmly.

| RB 2
G 3
Oct 26th (cont'd)
11.50am |

R.B. report enemy has again retired from in front of the SEAFORTHS.

| R.B. 3
12 noon |

1st Cav Brig send report of dispositions and movements of 1st Corps 7th Div and Cavalry Divisions on our left.

| G.A. 87
1.15pm |

R.B. report Enemy's heavy shell falling near northern corner of farm North of R in DES RABEQUES. This fire did no damage and only lasted a short time.

| R.B. 4
6.5pm |

Orders were received from 4th Div for an officer to proceed to H.Qrs 10th Brig at HOUPLINES to find out the exact position of the left of their second line. The Brig Major went over at 8.30pm.

| G.G. 1
9.35pm |

4th Div report that the attack of 1st Corps is proceeding favourably. 2 guns have been captured and many prisoners taken.

| G.G. 9
| | App 50
Following documents attached: (1) Message from Lord Kitchener d/. 26.10.14; (2) Information for troops; (3) Memo from 4th Div re method of meeting enemy's heavy bombardment of our trenches; (4) A sketch map showing position of E. LANCS Hants trenches as BUCY-LE-LONG 2.10.14
Oct 27th   CAFÉ ROYAL PLOEGSTEERT.
12.55am |

12th Brig report that the enemy appear to be retiring, confirmation is desired.

| G. 2
5.55am |

Report sent to 4th Div'n, after receipt of Bn reports, that situation is normal after quiet night, no indication of retirement of enemy. Patrols report enemy heard erecting obstacles in front of our left section.

| B.M. 2
7.40am |

An instance of successful cooperation between Infantry and Artillery at FRELINGHEM village is reported by B.G.C. to 4th Div'n.

| B.M. 5
10.19am |

KINGS OWN officer reports to 4th Div having counted 56 dead germans in front of one of their detached forward trenches.

| G. 19
10.35am |

Sketch map sent in by 14th Brig R.F.A. showing their zone of fire.

| App 51. (Summary of Information Oct 26th is attached to App 51.)
11.12am |

E. LANCS report enemy shelling houses at LE GHEER cross roads.

| E.L. 1
11.30am |

5th DRAGOON GUARDS reported in touch with SOMERSETS left.

Civilians carried on their work of digging second line trenches during the day.

|
12.20pm |

R.B. report having sent out patrol in north easterly direction which drew a good deal of fire. 40 men were counted in one trench.

| R.B. 7
5pm |

SOMERSETS report enemy collecting in farm and wood south east of R in DOUVE R and ask for one reserve company to clear them out, but B.G.C. thinks this inadvisable.

| B.G. 2
10.42pm |

4th Divn states that arrangements are benig made to shell the above farm.

| G. 21
Oct 27th (cont'd)
10.50pm |

4th Div report general situation.

| G. 21
11.5pm |

HANTS are warned that one company may have to act in the direction of LE GHEER tonight & arrangements must be made accordingly.

| B.M. 19
Oct 28th   CAFÉ ROYAL PLOEGSTEERT.
3.5am |

Somersets report farm buildings referred to last night as well alight but will want shelling again tomorrow.

| App 52. Attached: (1) Message from Lo Kitchener; (2) Summary of Information 27th Oct; (3) Information about Engagements with the Enemy.
6am |

All Battalions report quiet night, situation unchanged. The above farm except dwelling house was destroyed by our guns last night.

| B.M. 1
10.30am |

E. LANCS and RB report progress of work on new trenches.

| B.M. 5, R.B. 2
11.5am |

R.B. report having seen 200 of the enemy yesterday evening advancing along the west side of FRELINGHEM at a distance of 800 yds with mixed uniforms.

| R.B. 3
11.5am |

R.B. report having seen 200 of the enemy yesterday evening advancing along the west side of FRELINGHEM at a distance of 800 yds with mixed uniforms.

About noon instructions were given for the HANTS to take over the SOMERSETS trenches tonight.

| R.B. 3
B.M. 3
9pm |

4th Div report situation unchanged.

| G.6
11pm |

HANTS report having completed taking over trenches from SOMERSETS.

|
Oct 29th   CAFÉ ROYAL PLOEGSTEERT.
6am |

All Battalions report situation normal, 11th Brig report to 4th Div.

A very quiet morning.

| B.M. 1
1.37pm |

E. LANCS H.Qrs moved from cross roads LE GHEER to a farm house 150x east on the LE GHEER - PLOEGSTEERT road; their old H.Qr was heavily shelled.

| E.L. 7
4.5pm |

R.B. report enemy preparing footbridges over the river, stating that there are alread 3 trestle on the river at one spot. They ask for authority for Artillery to shell it. M.G.C. refers to the 4th Div for their authority.

| R.B. 29, B.G. 4
6pm |

An attack is commenced on the E. LANCS trenches about LE GHEER, artillery support is promptly asked for from Pt 63 and very promptly given with excellent results.

| B.M. 12-13-15-16-17-18
R.B. 11
E.L. 5-8
vide message from HANTS timed 8.15pm
6.40pm |

The attack was easily repulsed and all was quiet again by 6.40pm.

|
7.30pm |

Congratulations were received on the successful repulse of this attack from 4th Div & 10th I. Bde.

| G.6, H.86
Oct 29th (cont'd)
8.25pm |

R.B. report considerable movement of troops and transport across their front from right to left. They state that their patrols observed one of our shells to fall in the middle of a camp fire and another apparently stampeded their transport.

| R.B. 14. Also unnumberd message from HANTS received 10.30pm
9.35pm |

E. LANCS send in sketch of their trenches. vide Appendix 53.

| E.L. 10
9.35pm |

4th Div report on general situation.

| G. 9
| | App 53 attached: (1) Summary of Information 28th Oct; (2) Sketch of situation of armies on the VISTULA
Oct 30th   CAFÉ ROYAL PLOEGSTEERT.
6am
6.35am |

All Battalions report quiet night, but continuous movement of enemy's transport from south to north, this report sent on to 4th Div.

| B.M. 1
7.20am |

HANTS report ST YVES being heavily shelled with Heavies and shrapnel necessitating their moving theitr Headquarters to the edge of the wood South West of ST YVES, this was preliminary to a very heavy artillery bombardment of the whole line of our trenches with no sort of lull till about 11.30 am.

|
7.58am |

At 8 am the SOMERSETS were ordered to bring 2 coys forwards to the cross roads at PLOEGSTEERT and the E. LANCS two reserve coys to be ready for immediate action.

| B.M. 5-6
8.5am
10.27am |

Soon after 8 am the enemy's infantry commenced a half hearted attack on the R.B. but were reported retiring at 10.27 and collecting opposite their right centre.

MESSINES on our left was at the same time heavily bombarded.

| G. 60
1.15pm |

R.B. report main attack drifting to their left & dying away in their front.

| R.B. 15
1.20pm |

Aeroplane report situation. vide App 54.

| R.B. 15
1.30pm |

Artillery on Pt 63 report Enemy's captive balloon beyond the range of our guns.

| I95
2.25pm |

HANTS report their left centre trench being particularly heavily shelled and attach a report from Lieut ATCHISON stating that the enemy are holding a new trench 400 yds in front of him, and that two of his trenches have been blown to bits.

|
2.50pm |

O.C. HANTS sends in a further report from LIEUT ATCHISON timed 2.30pm stating that one of their platoons had been practically wiped out and asking for reinforcements.

|
2.57pm |

The enemy at this time appeared to be concentrating in a farm 700 yds east of HANTS left Coy HdQrs and up the river WARNAVE. Artillery cooperation is asked for.

| E.L. 10
B.M. 23-24-40
4.6pm |

HANTS report that their left centre Coy is suffering heavily and that the enemy are establishing themselves within 300 yds of this Coy. Instructions are given to SOMERSETS to reinforce this Coy if possible.

| B.M. 27-32
4.18pm |

12th Brigade (in accordance with instructions from 4th Div vide Q13) report that ROYAL INNISKILLEN FUSILIERS are on their way to PLOEGSTEERT.

| B.M. 31
5.3pm
5.10pm |

SOMERSETS report having sent out one platoon at 4.5pm to reinforce HANTS left centre coy and say they will send another platoon at dusk.

Later at 5.10pm they send 3 more platoons to reinforce them.

| S.L. 6
5.23 |

HANTS left centre trench has been destroyed by shell fire and the situation is reported as critical. The enemy are reported moving from right to left and concentrating between ST YVES and RIVER DOUVE. The 14th Brig R.F.A. is asked to shell them.

| B.M. 42
6pm |

The Div Cyclist Coy is placed at the disposal of O.C. SOMERSETS to hold the main road between MESSINES bridge and the CHATEAU.

The INNISKILLENS reached PLOEGSTEERT at about this time.

| B.M. 44
6.13pm
6.18pm |

O.C. 32nd Brig R.F.A. reports that the enemy have broken through our line in the centre of the HANTS trenches, whereupon the M.G.C. sends a company if INNIS FUS to O.C. SOMERSETS so that he may have his whole battalion for offensive action in counter attacking the enemy.

| 202
B.M. 45
6.25pm |

O.C. HANTS reports having consulted with O.C. SOMERSETS and states that the latter is restoring his line with one company and a second coy held in reserve. He estimates the enemy's strength as two battalions on left centre and about the same on right centre.

|
7.39pm |

1st Cav Div report they are being heavily attacked at MESSINES and have no reserve to cooperate with us.

|
Oct 30th (cont'd)
8.18pm |

M.G.C. orders Divn Squadron to the trenches N.E. of Pt 63 to arrange for protection of guns on Pt 63 in conjunction with Div Cyclists. One Coy INNES FUS is occupying the trenches E of MESSINES road backing up the HANTS.

| B.M. 52
8.28pm |

Major PROWSE is ordered to take direction of affairs on the left.

| B.M. 53
8.30pm |

O.C. SOMERSETS reports he has cleared the situation, but that the trenches which have been so badly damaged by shell fire will require redigging, and arranges accordingly.

|
8.47pm |

R.B. report enemy digging a very strong earthwork in the angle formed by the LE BIZET - LE TOUQUET and the LE GHEER - LE TOUQUET roads about 250 yds from their nearest trench.

| R.B. 23
9.40pm |

M.G.C. reports restoration of the situation on his left to 4th Div, and recommends MAJOR PROWSE for immediate promotion to LT COL.

| BM 54
10pm |

CAPT CLAYHILLS report of what has happened during the day received, he states that the enemy's casualties appear to have been small.

|
10.19pm |

12th Brig reports that two Coys LANC FUS left at 9.10pm for PLOEGSTEERT.

| BM 50
10.40pm |

4th Div order LANC FUS less 2 Coys to join other 2 Coys at PLOEGSTEERT by 5am tomorrow.

| G 34
10.47pm |

2 Coys LANC FUS arrived, & were billeted in old factory, 400 yds S of Brig H.Qrs.

| BM 62
11.7pm |

O.C. HANTS reports that enemy has occupied Estaminet in ST YVES and 2 of our trenches just south of it. He states that Maj Prowse has drawn round the enemy an inner ring of troops from his reserve. He asks for a gun to blow up the Estaminet.

|
11.25pm |

O.C. SOMERSETS reports having a prisoner from 134th SAXONS 19th Corps.

| SL 10
| | App 54 attached: (1) Summary of Information 29th Oct; (2) Sketch of French Dirigible
Oct 31st   CAFÉ ROYAL PLOEGSTEERT.
12.7am |

Divn Cyclists report that INNES FUS have taken over trenches at X roads 500x N of CHATEAU. The Div Cyclists now hold the line of road from INNES FUS left to Bridge over DOUVE R.

|
1.15am |

O.C. SOMERSETS reports he is proceeding to take the two trenches of HANTS now occupied by Enemy. Also the ESTAMINET & houses. An account of this affair is attached to App 55. It appears that after a heavy bombardment in which the trenches on the North of ST YVES road and the two which are astride the road running east from the ESTAMINET held by LIEUT TRIMMERS's platoon were all badly damaged, it was against the latter two trenches that the attack was pushed home and eventually penetrated our line. LIEUT TRIMMER and his men appear to have fought to the last and all were killed except one man who was badly wounded. The enemy, about 60 of them, advanced about 50 yards West of the road but were forced to retire, LIEUTS ATCHINSON and WADE (HANTS REGT) having constructed a barricade on the road at the North End of the cutting and mounted a machine gun there. The Enemy did not attempt to establish themselves in the buildings.

| vide report
4am |

LANC FUS less 2 coys arrived at PLOEGSTEERT.

|
5am |

2 coys INNES FUS moved to road junction north of S in BOIS-DE-PLOEGSTEERT.

| BM 4
5.15am |

O.C. SOMERSETS reports the situation cleared up. He puts 1 Coy S.L.I and a machine gun into the trenches to relieve the HANTS and 1 Coy in close support.

|
6.14am |

Divn Cyclists & Div Cav are recalled to their billets.

|
6.35am |

O.C. INNES FUS after consulting with O.C. WILDES RIFLES and the adjutant 5th D.G.S. sends in report. vide App 55.

|
7.12am |

R.B. report that enemy's infantry was last night heard moving in a southerly direction through FRELINGHEM. They had a quiet night.

| RB 1
7.7am |

HANTS report Enemy forming for attack in front of their right centre company, and on their extreme left. Artillery on Pt 63 is asked to cooperate.

| BM 9
7.20am |

1st Cav Brig from MESSINES report they are being heavily attacked and would like support if possible. 2 Coys INNES FUS are sent North of DOUVE R to join the Coy already there, to assist them.

| 396 & BM 13
Oct 31st (cont'd)
10.15am |

1st Cav Div report they have been obliged to fall back slowly to a N & S line through G of WULVERGHEM owing to the gap made by the retirement of the 57th Rifles.

| I(g)80
11.56am |

E. LANCS report 50 germans killed & about 100 wounded in the attack yesterday.

| E.L. 8
1.6pm |

4th Div states that K.O.S.B.s and K.O.Y.L.I should by now have arrived to assist 1st Cav Divn at MESSINES. They were sent up in motor buses.

| G 8
N.B. |

The attack reported by HANTS at 7.7am to be developing does not appear to have come to anything.

| App 55
1.20pm |

M.G.C. sends report to 4th Div that INNIS FUS are making good progress South of MESSINES and that the enemy are retiring.

| BM 19
2.27pm |

MESSINES reported recaptured and enemy holding ridge east of it.

| Message from I.F. timed 2pm, BM 24-25-27
3.32pm |

HANTS report heavy bombardment of trenches began at 2.45pm and is still continuing, some m.g. fire and rifle fire is also going in.

|
5.5pm |

INNIS FUS report enemy have been moving from east of MESSINES to southward, they ask if RA can destroy a m. gun that is worrying them from a farm about 250 yds in front of their trenches. A sketch showing the position of their trenches is attached to this message.

|
6pm |

HANTS report that CAPT WATSON's Coy (SOMERSETS left centre trench) has suffered many casualties and ask for reinforcements as enemy will probably attack tonight.

|
6.20pm |

E. LANCS report H.Q.rs moved to a cottage near PLOEGSTEERT on the LE GHEER - PLOEGSTEERT road, as they have been shelled out of their last house.

| E.L. 13
6.27pm |

Fighting still reported going on in MESSINES.

| G.G. 7
7.35pm |

R.B. report their centre & left have been shelled during the afternoon and that the germans are still digging S.E. of the railway.

| R.B. 11
7pm |

½ Coy E. LANCS is sent to reinforce right Coy HANTS.

| B.M. 34-36
Oct 31st (cont'd)
8.1pm |

SOMERSETS say they would be glad of 50 LANC FUS. They state that CAPTS JONES-MORTIMER and SMITH were wounded by shell fire.

Two platoons A Coy were sent to reinforce HANTS left by the river as they were reported hard pressed. They report several casualties, also that 75 dead germans were found on the Entanglements of HANTS trench which was rushed yesterday.

|
8.52pm |

HANTS ask for artillery fire to be directed on burnt farm 500 yds in front of his D Coy trench.

|
9.40pm |

1st Cav Div is asked whether the INNIS FUS North of DOUVE River can now be relieved with safety.

| B.M. 50
10.40pm |

HANTS send in report re situation during the day attached to App 55.

| G 80
10.45pm |

1st Cav Div report that it will not be possible to relieve INNIS FUS 3 Coys North of DOUVE before tomorrow.

|
11.33pm |

Orders are sent to HANTS & SOMERSETS to sort out their companies tonight. Two platoons HANTS are now available in reserve to fill gaps in HANTS front line. All trenches are to be improved in view of a probable attack tomorrow after the heavy Artillery bombardment.

| B.M. 53

11th Infantry Brigade, War Diary, December 1914

Appendix 112

TNA: WO 95/1488/2/4, p245

TO: 4th Div.
Sender's Number: BM 20 | Day of Month: 25th | In reply to Number:

From communications today between our men and the Germans in front of us it is quite clear that they are still part of Nineteenth Corps aaa They are SAXONS coming from CHEMNITZ aaa CAPT MAUD's body was brought in by them this evening

From | 11th Brig
Place |
Time | 5 pm

TNA: WO 95/1488/2/4, p246

TO: All units.
Sender's Number: BM 4 | Day of Month: 26th | In reply to Number:

If there should be any informal cessation of fire today or at any time as there was yesterday great care should be taken that the enemy is not allowed in sight of our trenches and entanglements as he would thereby gain most valuable information

From | 11th Brig
Place |
Time | 8.30 am

TNA: WO 95/1488/2/4, p247

Report on proceedings to the front of the Hampshire Regt trench on Christmas day.

The night 24/25 was particularly free from sniping to our front. The enemy were singing christmas carols and their national songs. About 10 am on Christmas morning I was making a sketch of the trench under cover of fog, when I saw several of the enemy approaching from the trench north of our T piece. I shouted out for them to halt not firing as the enemy was without arms. This was complied with and I sent forward a patrol to state that they must approach no nearer and return to their trench or I should open fire. The enemy then returned to their trench. Soon after more of the enemy were seen approaching from their main trench to the East of our position. These men also were halted and a patrol sent forward. As the patrol seemed unable to induce the enemy to return to their trenches and more were seen approaching I went forward and asked to see an officer. An under officer came forward, but I failed to make him understand me. An interpreter however was soon produced and the enemy asked that there should be no shooting as it was Christmas day and that they should be allowed to bury their dead of which there were a considerable number a short way in front of their trench. This request I granted as by this time considerable numbers were walking about outside their trenches. A spot was indicated just by their foremost dead which I informed them if they passed I should be compelled to open fire and that after dusk I should open fire on anyone outside the trench. The enemy agreed to these conditions and kept to them throughout the day. Towards evening what looked like a Staff Officer appeared and ordered all back to the trenches which order was immediately complied with. To our right front a gathering of some two to three hundred men of both sides took place, the men exchanging gifts, handing overs enemy's dead from near our trenches, and even exchanging rifles. Throughout the day I kept the garrison of my trench from contact with the enemy the men not being allowed out on the enemy's side. I gained the following information as regards the enemy and his trenches and dispositions.

The men were well clothed and seemed well supplied. Every man was wearing a pair of gum-boots. The regiments represented were 132, 133 & 134 and some men with F.A. under a Crown, the great majority belonging to the 133rd regiment. The men seemed in age to range between nineteen and forty-five. They seemed very simple minded creatures, and were much elated over alleged victories in Russia. They stated they wished the war would soon finish, but were confident of their success. The strength to our immediate front I estimated to be about one man to every two yards except on right front, where they appeared to be much stronger there being at least on man per yard looking over the parapet even after a considerable number had left the trench.

The wire in front of enemy's trenches was mounted on wooden frames with cross pieces at either end three feet high. The men appeared to have no difficulty in stepping over these. I could not see if there was trip wire in addition. The trenches appeared to be in good condition, the men jumped in from the parapet without splashing about. The trenches are loopholed about eighteen inches off the ground (in the front trench) these were about ten feet apart. Three lines of trenches were observed, the rear line being about six hundred yards from the front line, these were connected with communication trenches. There appeared to be wire netting over the trenches coming above the parapet. A fortified house about [figure missing: pencilled note, initialled FRH: "will get this"] yards in rear of enemy's barricade on the north side of the Le Gheer road was observed. I could see no maxim guns or emplacements.

JDM Beckett, Capt

O.C. C Coy

Hampshire Regt

[pencilled note: "Forwarded FR Hicks, Mjr"]

War Diary – 11 Inf Bde

December 1914

Hour, Date, Place

|

Summary of Events and Information

|

Remarks

1st Dec.   4.5 am
Pt 20 Farm |

Situation reported normal.

| B.M.1, B.M.13 App 86
6.50 pm |

Shelling.

Somerset section | nil
Rif Brig section | nil
Hants section | nil
E Lan section | 8 small shells on left trench about 9.15 am. None blind.

Work.

Somerset section | Right trench reconstructed owing to flooding.
Rif Brig section | Breastwork in firing line improved. Supporting trenches for Hants continued. Wire put out.
Hants section | Main trench improved. facings made, faggots collected.
E Lan section | Work on 2nd line trench & communication trench to Convent. Fire trenches deepened & cleaned.

200 men work on main Breastwork line

new German trench dug south of south face of left trench of Somersets.

Following reinforcements joined night of 30th Nov. Somersets 1 officer, 50 O.R. E Lan 1 officers 154 O.R. Rif Brig. 25 O.R.

|

K | W | S
Somersets | - | 1 | -
E. Lan | - | - | -
Hants | - | - | 4
Rif Brig | - | - | 7
London RB | - | - | 20
Total 32 | - | - | 31

Hour, Date, Place

|

Summary of Events and Information

|

Remarks

2nd Dec.   4 am
Pt 20 Farm |

Situation reported normal.

| B.M.1, B.M.3 App 87
9.5 am |

Somersets report work on new German trench stopped. Mostly demolished by shell fire yesterday.

|
6.25 pm |

Shelling. More than usual.

Somerset section | About 2 heavy howitzers & 4 shrapnel an hour from WARNETON & DEULMONT directions. None blind.
Rif Brig section | 5 white holes near trenches. 2 blind in front.
Hants section | Small gun fired 12 shells about 10 a.m. at end of main trench by tunnel. 2 blind.
E Lan section | 10 heavy shells at Convent about 10 a.m. & again at 2 p.m. 10 more. 2 blind. 10 Little Willies at Burnt Fm in front of Convent. 12 large shells over left trench about 10 a.m.

Work.

150 men in two reliefs in Breastwork line. London RB on 2nd line.

Somerset section | Communication trench dug. Latrines & drainage improved.
Rif Brig section | Construction of overhead cover & obstacles continued.
Hants section | Wiring & obstacles continued. Communications trenches deepened etc.
E Lan section | Work on 2nd line trench & communication trenches continued also fallen in trenches revetted.

No movement except reoccupation of GERMAN HOUSE.

HIS MAJESTY visited NIEPPE & inspected detachments of the Brigade.

|

K | W | S
Somersets | - | 1 | -
E. Lan | - | 1 | -
Hants | 1 | 1 | 3
Rif Brig | 1 | 2 | 4
London RB | - | 1 | 8
Total 23 | 2 | 6 | 15